[Music]
w
hello good day good evening everybody
and welcome back to the askit show today
is episode 236 and I'm going to be
taking questions only from the live chat
today it's a completely interactive
interactive episode absolutely no
pre-selected questions all right so
let's see before we begin who all is on
the live stream I can see Mao Perez from
txas Hello SOI jines sha P pakla parij
diit prar gup Tushar kalburgi hello ah
Namaste Ashish pandel Sona bravy astral
anant Pai kapalin vid Manar uh yes it's
on Miss VII manar's recommendation that
I'm doing this completely interactive
today so thank thank you ma'am for that
suggestion Shri Hari Arjun Shak Kari Mr
88 tripti Mishra Raj Ashish pandel
anupam jwal priyan sud Shas jadav
geopolitical dub from indor Rangers wolf
ainash Sur surj rout Saia again bries SK
supratim data Prav Sat by Rangers wolf
manuk Krishna Varun Xmas Yus Zas Krishna
goind Alfred runat BV Ry from is
Netherlands T Chandra meet Oscar Madison
manuk Krishna is astral goami a Shri
Hari Arjun surj kkar kartia Singh rajput
animish um Gokul Krishan John Cena anul
Jui um okay Jo guman tanai Chandra pan
Shetty man bear pig prar Mishra nishal
Ry samrat volcano Neo nomad Ronny green
re Reaper plays davic shrien samrat
Shukla a Aries manticor anul sinari
Abhishek sahu viraj o Kalani deshmuk
utsav katri random skull CH anti motion
Clips anit pradan
mlin really now bat G meet but Mr
Redbird and so and so many other people
so okay good evening good day everybody
thank you so much for being on this live
stream with that said please go ahead
didn't ask you questions I will take
questions only from the live chat today
so let's see what questions you all have
lot happening in the world
um let's
see okay what questions do we
have manuk Krishna says how would you
design an Indian Nation essentially that
would last 3,000 years from now how can
a nation grow in indefinitely without
collapsing like Rome or the cholas
that's an interesting question do we
know of any Nation or geopolitical
entity or any other such entity that has
existed for 3,000 years we know of
civilizations that have existed longer
we are the oldest continuously existing
civilization that still exists we
Indians India is the oldest continuously
existing civilization it's
not look this idea of a Nation that's a
pretty recent idea historically we had
culture and civilizations and we had
kingdoms and Empires nation states is a
very recent idea it's an artificial kind
of idea not sure how long it will last
yesterday I had a I did a podcast live
stream with Dr gutam Des Raju and he
says that the Age of Empires is upon us
again and we're going to have four
Empires going forward which is the US
China Russia and India so uh the nation
state system is an experiment a
temporary exp experiment it will not not
last uh very long so in that sense I do
conquer with what Dr D Raju said
yesterday I agree with with what he said
so nations are an artificial enti
kingdoms and Empires that's something
that historically has existed so let's
say you want an Empire that lasts 3,000
years well the first question you ask
yourself is has there ever been an
Empire that lasted 3,000 years um the
answer is no
okay we've had dynasties that lasted
like 2,000 years the cholas lasted
almost 2,000 years as a
Dynasty uh definitely more than more
than a thousand years when you look at
the Roman Empire it lasted about let's
say 1500 years and some people would be
surprised because you would imagine that
the that Rome kind of disintegrated
around 500 roughly ad right but that's
the Western Roman Empire the Eastern
Roman Empire based out of Constantinople
lasted until the 15th century it did
decline later and it was overrun by the
Turks eventually but Rome as an imperial
entity lasted about 1500 years so yeah
1500 years something can last what about
Egypt the Egyptian Empire you can say it
lasted 2,000 plus years so it's
something that's possible so yeah there
is some historical president but if
you're talking about 3,000 years you're
kind of pushing the boundaries of what
has historically occurred in the past
with all that said if you want not a
nation but an Empire the last 3,000
years first of all it needs to have a
very strong cultural and civil
civilizational uh scaffolding or super
structure that it builds upon it needs a
basis a long-term basis which is its
civilizational identity and cultural
identity so that's something we have
that's that's an advantage we have we
have a culture civilization that's
probably 10,000 or more years
old right so that's one great Advantage
we have the Chinese have a similar
Advantage their culture maybe 5,000 plus
years old perhaps yeah nobody else has
that that's sort of long long standing
longlasting culture or civilization so
we have we already have that so then we
need political
stability so you need a system a
political system that ensures there is
stability uh even after transitions from
one from one leader to the
next and obviously uh the the system
should be such that it picks the right
leader whenever the transition happens
when leader a Emperor a becomes old
let's say he or she is in his 70s 80s
and it's time to move on to the next
leader then the system should pick the
best possible next leader which means
that there should not be nepotism which
generally in Empires you have the eldest
son or the best son who takes takes uh
the throne or the the crown going
forward but I really want it to be non-
nepotistic so the system has to be such
that it will always pick the best
possible
successor so that you know the right
things keep on happening you know
strengthening the military strengthening
um you know focusing on the right things
like science and technology
strengthening culture all of that so you
need to have a system that takes care of
all these things so what do you need you
need a strong civilizational scaffolding
which we have you need a great education
system that teaches the citizens the
right values and critical thinking and
all of that science technology and
culture all of that you need that that's
what we don't have so that's one thing
that needs to be created our education
system is the one of the worst in the
world
today then you need a civilization
language one language okay not 78
languages and all that nonsense you need
one language that is the Supreme
language and all other languages are
subsidiary that's how it works in an
Empire
okay democracy doesn't really work too
much too
well democracy cre creates you know
disintegration so you need a hybrid
democracy like Dr de was saying
yesterday you need hybrid democracy a
hybrid model that's what I have been
saying for
years uh so you need that sort of system
so you know you need a good education
system you need a civilization strong
civilization scaffolding you need the
right system uh at the top which is a
non Democratic ruler because if a ruler
has to go and beg to the people every
five years based on popularity your
country your Empire Will Never Last you
need to pick the right people and let
them rule as long as they need to and
then the right sort of succession should
happen so the only way you can have
something that lasts 3,000 years if it's
possible is through an imperial system
not a nation state system or not through
democracy okay because historically
democracies have never worked
historically empires have
lasted Empire and civilizations so
that's what I would
do okay Nomad Ron says how do you how to
speak French like you well how to speak
French like me first of all you need to
study French and learn French learn the
basics it's not an easy language to
learn but it's an Indo European language
so it's not that hard for us as opposed
to let's say learning Chinese or Arabic
or Swahili or or or or algonkian or
something so French is an Indo European
language it's reasonably uh
similar uh to our our languages Indian
languages reasonably um so first of all
there's that so you have to go go
through it step by step you have to if
you want to learn a language you have to
immerse yourself in an environment where
that's the only language that's around
so that's obviously not possible if
you're living outside of
France but you need to spend a a set
number of minutes or hours every day
practicing learning you not pushing
yourself and look if you
really if you really want to learn a
language like really if you're desperate
to learn a language you can get a pretty
good working knowledge of a
language in a week's time if you
completely immerse yourself and you
force yourself to study the language in
a challenging manner like 10 12 hours a
day in a week's time you'll be speaking
whatever language you want in to a
reasonable level of competence I mean
you can converse with people
you're you'll speak broken kind of
French or whatever but at least you'll
be able to converse with people whether
it's French whether it's Italian Spanish
whatever language you can learn in a
week if you want but the point is if you
want to learn to high level of
proficiency you have to keep on doing it
over and over again for a long long
period of time now I learned French as a
kid okay and and as a as a kid you pick
up languages like like that it's very
fast it's very easy you don't even
realize when you learned I don't I did
not take French lessons or something I I
learned because I was immersed in a
French environment I learned I just
picked it up I did not take a single
French class or lesson I just picked it
up in like two three months so as a kid
you have that advantage that you absorb
languages very fast but as an adult if
you want to learn then you have to spend
time learning it systematically and to
speak it like a native probably I I have
the pronunciation of a native because I
lived in that I spent time in a fren
speaking environment significant amount
of time if you want to learn it like
that then you actually have to spend
time among the native speakers to pick
up those accents and those nuances so
that's what you need to do it's it
applies not just to French but to any
language
whatsoever all right um let's
see um um um um um um what other
questions do we have we have lots of
questions okay Rashmi says I want to
learn Sanskrit and I want to talk
fluently well it's
possible Sanskrit is our our mother
language actually I mean today nobody
says Sanskrit is their mother tongue
everybody has some language you know uh
and our languages are upper Branch
languages whether whe it
is whatever Hindi marati Telugu uh
Bengali Gujarati Tamil Canada whatever
it is these are all newer languages um
they all have a lot of vocabulary that's
derived from Sanskrit I think Tamil must
have 40% Telugu must have
40% Malayalam must have about 50%
Sanskrit vocab ulary so we all use
Sanskrit vocabulary we all use
grammatical constructs that come out of
Sanskrit but we don't realize Sanskrit
is still more much more or less alive in
whatever languages we speak so if you
want to learn actual Sanskrit and speak
proper fluent Sanskrit once again you to
spend a couple of hours every day
studying so the best book I know of is a
book that's in Hindi not it's not in
English it's called Sanskrit swam
shikshak Sanskrit shik Shak it's a
pretty cheap book and if you study that
book like an hour a day in three months
you'll be probably speaking Sanskrit
you'll be able to Converse in Sanskrit
and that will give you the the
foundation to learn Sanskrit to whatever
level of competence influence that you
want so if you really want to do
something well get going no one's
stopping you and uh all the all the
information that you need is available
for pretty cheap that book sunkit so may
cost I don't know 100 200 bucks I'm sure
anybody can afford that if you are a
student maybe you can save spend some
time in saving money save money and buy
it so yeah if you take that book and if
you already know Hindi you'll be able to
speak Sanskrit have a conversation in
Sanskrit in three months and then you
keep studying and you can be you can
speak
fluently okay VII says what do you think
about the idea of having my own mental
health company providing Therapies
combined with ancient Indian knowledge
instead of working in anti-india steak
snake pits and schools I think it's a
great idea look uh mental health is a
challenge for a lot of people today
today's environment is pretty stressful
we have an overload of noise and
information in in the past the world was
much slower paced to the world is fast
paced it's changing a lot so many new
things happening all the
time um so a lot of people seem to be
facing mental health challenges I
remember about five years ago during the
lockdown it was a very very big deal
this mental health thing uh every other
podcast was talking about mental health
those days and I think it's it's always
been a challenge for a lot of people in
the past it was you do not really speak
about that but now it's okay to speak
about it apparently uh so I think it's
it's uh if you want to have start a
company that provides therapies and
solutions uh to mental health issues I
think it's an evergreen field and if you
if your therapies and and solutions that
you provide are good then you will do
really well right so it's it's a great
idea but to succeed ideas aren't enough
you need the right kind of execution uh
so I think it's a great idea you need to
learn you need to know how to execute it
well maybe uh you can you know look at
case studies as to how companies succeed
and fail how to create a startup or all
of that stuff I think it's a great idea
uh but don't just jump into it do a
little bit of due diligence a little bit
of research understand how to create a
startup and all that and you will need
some funding as well all that stuff will
be will be there but I think these days
funding and everything is available much
it's much easier to get it than than
before I think it's a great idea uh and
yeah if if you're not happy with
wherever you're working uh it's
something that is certainly something
worth uh doing so yes I would say it's
it's a it's a good idea it's a good idea
right so all the best all the best
ma'am um sham rur says what are the
relations what's the relationship
between the Romani people and the
banjaras that's an interesting question
so let's talk about first of all who are
the Romani people and then who are the
Banjara people right let's talk about
the banjaras first so the banjaras are a
nomadic Community or a set of nomadic
communities uh in that live in India
today
now uh they generally seem to be
associated with places like uh northern
and western India Rajasthan Gujarat and
they are given they're called by
different names in different places but
overall they are called banjaras right
they are nomadic people they don't live
in one place they move from place to
place and that sort of thing uh and and
what's the origin there seem to be
various theories of origins of the
banjaras one of the uh stories that one
hears is that some of these Banjara
people are the descendants of the
soldiers of various rajput Kings who
fought uh the the Turks and lost and
refused to surrender and went out and
lived in the forests people like U um
Maharana Pratap uh Rak Kumba Etc one
hears that their soldiers never ever
surrendered they went and lived in the
forest and their descendants still uh
live a nomadic
life um and maybe so that's one uh
origin story and I'm sure there is a lot
of truth behind that I'm sure it doesn't
it doesn't apply to all Banjara people
but many of them and maybe some other
people always lived nomadically I'm not
really sure I've not really studied and
done the research into their Origins I'm
not sure Indian historians have done
proper research about this but yes it's
it's a nomadic community and uh they
they typically are employed not employed
but their profession generally is uh
singing dancing all of that they they do
folk singing and all and uh they they
have kept kept lots of folk tunes Etc
alive through their music uh and so on
and so that's the banjaras and the
Romani people
are Indian origin people who are nomadic
people in Europe and they have faced
persecution and horrible oppression for
the past 1,000 years now what's the
origin of the Romani people they are
also called
gypsies so in the past in Europe it was
believed in Europe that these people
were of Egyptian Origins so they were
called Egyptians and eventually called
gypsies but these people they call
themselves either Romani or
cinti yeah and there are other names
applied to them KH Kash and so
on um so the origin these people this
speak an a language that is very closely
related to Gujarati Rajasthani and
Punjabi West Northern and Western Indian
languages very closely related to these
languages I think these three languages
Gujarati Rajasthani Punjabi are the
three closest languages today to the uh
Romani
language so how did these people end up
in Europe so there are multiple uh
theories to that as well uh Dr Ian
Hancock is the first Romani person ever
to get a PhD okay so today the Romani
people they they have European names
mostly and uh they have adopted various
uh langu sorry various religions just to
survive so most of them in Europe would
be Christians today and the ones who
live in other countries like turkey they
would be Muslims today some of them some
Romani people live in Egypt they are
Muslims there some Romani people live in
uh many Romani people live in Turkey
today about probably about 5% at least
of turkey's population could be of
Romani origin and they're all Muslims
okay they all practice Islam and in
Europe most of them are Christians many
of them are kind
of perhaps reverting to some form of
dharmic practice and so on but yeah at
least nominally most of them practice
these other religions uh so what's the
origin story and and the Romani people
have been horribly persecuted in Europe
uh there are places in the past places
like Germany and other other countries
where if you were Romani you would just
be you know uh automatically sentenced
to death so many lots of romanis were
just killed just for existing for being
Romani many of them were enslaved for
for generations for centuries and even
today they are like second class
citizens in most European countries they
are still
despised they not allowed to to settle
in cities and they are made to exist on
the fringes of society many of them
don't have proper documentation which
means they are essentially stateless
even today they are treated with a
tremendous amount of racism and uh they
are some of the most brilliant brilliant
people in Europe today many footballers
many of the top footballers in Europe
are of Romani origin Erik Kona one of
the greatest French footballers one of
the legends of Manchester United Eric
Kona who is today uh an actor now you
want to look see what it looks like
let's let's take a look at Eric Kona one
of the absolute legends of football he
is of Romani origin let us go here Eric
Kona so that is Eric Kona and he was one
of the great French footballers U and
Manchester United footballers one of the
absolute greats and a bad boy of
football who else do we have
Pirlo
purlo yes
Romani uh again give you so many okay
let's just see Romani footballers Romani
foot football players here we have it so
many Kona Georg Hai kesma
christov Pirlo uh possibly possibly
possibly Ronaldo I'm not sure
uh uh so many I can give you
examples uh Andrea Pio obviously uh who
else do we have Quaresma is one of the
great uh I believe Michael balak Milan
baros yes uh Michael balak of of of
Germany uh slatan Ibrahimovic is said to
to be of Romani origin and who else do
we have Romani footballers there's
there's so many names here um yeah so I
I'll not go into all the details but you
get the point and when it comes to uh
people from other fields some of the
greatest musicians of all time in Europe
are of Romani origin Jango Reinhardt
gypsy jazz Jango you know what Django
actually meant it meant Jago wake up
Jango
Reinhardt have you heard of Le Zeppelin
Le Zeppelin right I think some of you
may know about Le Zeppelin their lead
singer Robert Plant the guy who looks
like a
viking he his mother was Gypsy Romani
and so on um
so that's who the Romani people are now
their origin is I'll tell you what the
origin story most likely is Dr Ian hanok
says that they are of rajput origin uh
so when people like the goris and gaves
and the Turks they attacked India they
took back uh millions of Indians as
slaves okay
um many of them many of these Indians
who were taken as slaves died in the
Hindu Kos mountains that's why the
mountains are called the hindukush
mountains the killer of Hindus and the
rest who survived ended up in the slave
bazaars of of Samaran bukara
Etc and maybe at some point in time they
took too many slaves and they didn't
want to execute them and you know create
a blood bath in those places in India it
was fine so maybe they just took a whole
bunch of people and said get the hell
out of here but you're not allowed to go
back to India go west and maybe that was
the origin of the Romani people we don't
we're not quite sure how it began but it
most likely originated in the slave
bazars of Samaran and bukar and the in
the turkic and Arabic World maybe there
was a surplus of slaves taken from India
and the Surplus slaves were just told to
push off but westwards not back to India
and probably that is the origin of the
Romani people so so the Romani and
Banjara aren't related the relation is
that they are both of Indian origin
obviously right but many of the Romani
people today in Europe some of them um
look kind of European because some of
them have intermarried at some point in
time some of their ancestors some of
them look very Indian some of them look
very very European most of them look
more Indian than European so that's the
deal with the Romani
people right okay some more questions
What U rudra manhas says Manas says is
the United States in Decline really why
does every analyst say that the US is
not a superpower anymore I don't know
what analyst you look you listening to
those analysts are idiots there are lots
of look if you're listen to Indian
analysts I'm sorry but these people
are they want to sens sensationalize
stuff uh these days it's all about G Raj
deep State us is declining nonsense
these people are
clueless uh I will not take any
specificness because I don't follow any
of them so I have no idea what who is
saying what okay
uh let's look at the ground reality
today okay of the United States and the
global geopolitical order if we look at
the military strength of the US today
and the kind of uh destructive power it
has at its disposal and the kind of uh
Global geopolitical footprint it has and
the kind of power projection abilities
the US has I it it is absolutely clear
that the US has never been more powerful
than it is
today the US has never had as much
destructive power at its disposal than
it has today military power and its
Global power projection is all over the
place they have military bases more than
8009 more than 800 military bases
outside their territory across the world
spread across the world they can project
power anywhere they want they can
intervene militarily anywhere in the
world at 30 to 60 minutes notice you
call that a nation in Decline really
power in Decline they are a power in the
ascendancy and they are on the verge of
becoming a hyper power from a superpower
AI the AI race whoever wins that and
they are they have the most uh biggest
advantage in the AI race right now so
the AI race is one thing and then
there's the space race and the US is
clearly winning the space race at this
at this stage in time U they are the
only nation that have the ability right
now to send people to Mars and to the
moon and to colonize Moon and in the
Mars so by 2030 31 they're going to have
people on on on the moon sorry on Mars
and pro on the moon also so when you
have a footprint on the moon on Mars you
are winning the AI race and you have a
global geopolitical power projection
ability that allows you to intervene at
60 minutes notice anywhere in the
world and you control the global Reserve
currency and everything do you call that
a nation in Decline you call that power
in Decline I don't know what these
people are smoking or drinking okay
these so-called analysts that say that
the US is a is not a superpower anymore
do they even I mean what is their
definition of the term superow
are when you use a term you need to know
exactly how to define it uh that's
something that's inbuilt in me because
uh of a scientific background uh you
don't use terms Loosely you have to know
exactly what the definition of any term
that you use is so from my perspective
the term superpower what does it mean it
means an a power that can intervene
anywhere in the world at 60 minutes
notice let's say 30 minutes 60 Minutes 1
Hour 2 hour whatever again intervene
anywhere in the world on
demand that's a superpower and there's
only one nation in the world that can do
it that's the US sure Russia
can you know eliminate any country in
the world at 60 minutes notice but they
can't put boots on the ground at 60
minutes notice the Russians the US in an
hour or two they can have boots on the
ground essentially anywhere in the
world because they have military bases
all across the world spread everywhere
so the US can do it Russ can't do it and
China is far away from doing
that so the US is the only superpower
and it's a superpower in the
ascendancy it's actually getting
stronger yes U the outcome of the AI
race will determine who is going to be
ruling the world for the next 10,000
years China is a big participant in that
so the US is very much uh neck to neck
you could say Perhaps Perhaps Perhaps
with China at least from what one sees
in the public domain it looks like it's
NE to NE to race but the US has a big
head start over the
Chinese and what's happening behind
closed doors is anyone's guess what kind
of capabilities the AI systems have
behind closed doors because I assure you
that what you see in public is only 1%
of what's out there in terms of AI so if
you if you think that chat GPT version
whatever is the best most powerful AI
that we have today I assure you that the
hidden AI systems that they have are at
least 100 times more powerful which
means that they probably have AGI
systems and Asi probably close to ASI
systems it's possible so whichever
nation has reached that stage is going
to rule the world so India is out of the
race clearly so is Russia probably
unless they have something up their
sleeve um so I don't agree with these
analysts who claim that the US is a
nation or or a power in Decline these
people have no idea what they're talking
about absolutely no
idea right
uh let's see interesting questions
interesting questions
um okay geopolitical dub says I saw your
conversation with gurudev Shri sh Rish
Shankar G can you tell more about the
original shieling how big was it then we
have no idea we don't know how large it
was it is supposed to have look
um I I think the eyewitness
accounts say that it was a pretty large
shieling not sure how large was it man
size what it was it 6 feet large was it
bigger than that was it smaller we're
not quite sure what we know is that it
was a levitating object it was a
levitating shivling what does levitating
mean it was floating in midair it was
floating in midair because of magnetic
properties so you can make a magnet
float in midair using other magnets you
can do that so this
object this shieling
one of the oldest shielings we had in
the in our civilization it was a
magnetically levitating object I'm not
sure how large it was okay um it looks
like it was whitish in
color and uh it was I mean when the
barbarians the Turks they arrived there
and they saw this they were stupified
they were staggered to see something
like that and they thought it was the
work of I don't know whatever you know
uh and yeah they they they broke it so I
we don't know much more than that about
the original Shing I haven't really read
the historical text that may or may not
describe what it originally looked like
but from what I know it was a pretty
large object and it was levitating
everybody agrees about that and it had
magnetic properties it was destroyed by
the Turks and disappeared for a thousand
years and now it has um it has now been
revealed to have been save saued by agot
bahans in the southern part of India for
a thousand years so when the destruction
of the somat Temple happened there were
Agri brahmins there in snat who
originated in Southern India and they
are the ones
who uh rescued the broken fragments of
the original sheling and took them back
took them down south to Southern India
and kept them hidden for a thousand
years and each fragment was shaped into
a sh shieling shape because once you
break a magnet you can't put it back
together again it won't become whole
again so each of the fragments was then
shaped into an you know into an
individual shieling and each fragment
was worshipped
separately and today the fragments U
I've seen at least four of those and
they still have magnetic properties if
you see the video the the conversation
that I had with gurv r Shankar G he
shows you know that they still have
magnetic properties it's very clear so
the that's what I can say about that and
if you see the conversation you'll know
that I have a a personal connection with
that with that original
shieling
um Mr 88 says how exactly did Europeans
conquer Africa and plunder Africa first
of all let's talk about why they did
this
uh
so Africa is the largest continent let's
take a we haven't seen the map today I
mean it's already been 35 minutes we
haven't opened the map what's
happening all right let's take a look at
the map here's the map we know where
India is let's go westwards and this is
Africa here all right and if you look at
the mer meraner projection map and so on
it will look like uh Eurasia is larger
than Africa and maybe the Americas are
similar size but I'll assure you that if
you look at the orig if you actually
look at the
and Africa is by far the largest
continent gigantic
continent um it's way bigger than every
other continent now so it it's Africa if
you look at the kind of resources it has
you will see that Africa holds more than
half of the world's natural
resources uh everything you can ask for
whether it is minerals whether it is
Metals iron copper
gold whatever raw materials need need of
any kind they're all available in Africa
you want uranium you'll find uranium in
Africa there tremendous amount of
fertile land if you want to do
Agriculture and so on and so forth
everything that you can ask for all raw
materials are available in Africa and
that's why Africa was was U seen as a
Gold Mine by the Europeans and that's
why they colonized parts of Africa and
there was a Scramble for Africa and the
European powers the colonizing powers in
the 19th century divided Africa up among
each among themselves
and that's why you see even today in
Africa you have Nations whose boundaries
are just straight lines because the lazy
colon colonizers when they eventually
departed they just you know Drew
straight line boundaries uh between
nations and these are all artificially
created
Nations and because these artificially
created Nations have ethnic groups
within them that historically did not
belong together that's why you have so
many Civil Wars and so much unrest in
Africa so why did the Europeans conquer
Africa and colonize Africa because of
the natural resources because
because I mean you know you want
resources you you want to enrich
yourself at somebody else's expense it's
as simple as that steal their resources
and use them uh that's why they did that
and how did they do it well the
Europeans already had a lot of uh
practice and experience colonizing other
countries like U the Americas they
destroyed uh
North America and South America they
wiped out the native cultures there
right and stole the land and they also
had experience the Europeans in India
how to suppress how to take over a very
large piece of territory and and uh and
uh suppress any descent and crush revols
and all that so they applied the same
techniques and learnings in Africa one
of the easiest things to do is divide
and conquer divide and Rule
so yeah so that's how they did it so the
Europeans had Superior technology they
had a lot of experience
fighting uh Nations and and kingdoms and
Empires that had uh man large Manpower
but inferior technology and they knew
how to uh divide and
Rule so that's why they were able to
gradually uh step by step in a
reasonably short period of time uh con
all of Africa so there are entire books
written about this but yeah it's an
interesting story as to how this
happened and it's it's tragic they've
completely destroyed Africa completely
destroyed Africa today if you see Africa
there are two major religions in Africa
both are of foreign origin both are
abrahamic religions and in some
countries both religions exist together
and there's a lot of Bloodshed because
of that and Africa's original cultures
have all been wiped out original
governance systems have all disappeared
uh Africans are rootless today they
don't know their history their history
has been eradicated their cultures have
been eradicated they worship foreign
gods and speak foreign languages just
like India where in in India everybody
thinks that speaking English Makes You
Makes You Superior to others and if you
speak English you can get good jobs if
you can't speak English you can't get
good jobs that sort of thing in Africa
it's mainly um either English or French
so there's lots of parts of Africa where
you if you want to appear civilized and
cultured you have to speak French so
once again let's go on the screen and
what are these nations I'm talking about
so I'm talking about the western African
nations the ecoas Nations the the
Nations where you have the CFA Frank
that's the currency uh Nations see if
you go to places like Libya Algeria
Morocco Western Sara morania Mali ner
Chad Bina Faso Sagal and so on and so
forth equator guine cun
y so on lots of these nations
uh these are frankophone frankophone
nations the other nations like in
southern parts of Africa Etc you speak
English there in South Africa you speak
either English or Africans Namibia again
English or Africans and so on so yeah
Africa is deeply deeply colonized even
today today it's colonized by proxy you
have uh dictators who run most of Africa
and the dictators are proxies for
foreign powers and so on so that is the
deal that's how it works in Africa
today
okay listen this question I've been
getting for so long why do the terms BC
and AD
exist why can't we simply say years ago
is it just the just the Christian
mindset at work here or is there
something useful in this penguin blue
waving tier
look why do the terms BC and AD exist
it's because of the Christian mindset we
don't need to use them but it's just a
convention you know if you have a degree
in history you want to use these terms
because it's every every
every uh academic domain has its
jargon it's it's the it's it's what the
people in the Inner Circle speak so if
you meet a bunch of people who are let's
say who have a background computer
science they will use computer science
jargon if you meet a bunch of physicists
they'll speak a different sort of
language that only they understand if
you meet a bunch of mathematicians they
have their own in inner terminology that
they use and others can't understand
similarly historians want to use certain
terminologies that that you know set
them apart from everybody else so they
want to use terms like PC and AD and
these it is CE and BCE so BC used to
mean before Christ ad means used to mean
anod Domino which means the year of Our
Lord what Lord God only knows the gods
only know it's a Christian God right
obviously BC means before Christ ad
means unno Domino today it is BCE and CE
c means Common Era and BCE means Before
Common ER what's the Common Era is a
Christian era so in the year one Mr
Christ is supposed to have been
born and so on so that's why these terms
exist these are eurocentric uh uh
Christian terms today they they try to
cloak that by using BCE and CE but it's
still the same thing so we certainly can
say years ago we certainly can uh but
then you have to keep on calculating see
you need a reference point somewhere I
say let's say I write an article in the
year uh
2015 and I say x number of years ago now
if you're reading this article in 2025
you may have to do a little bit of
mental calculation okay he wrote the
article in 2015 he said 387 years ago so
what does it exactly mean and what does
it mean from my perspective from 2025
it's a bit of a mental calculation and
most people can't do that math math
hurts people's brains right so that's
why you need a reference point
somewhere so that's that's why BC ad
works you know if you say 15 1456 ad ah
what happened then 1456 ad ah the
conquest of Constantinople by Saleem
whatever the hell he was
fat so so that bc8 thing it gives you a
reference point of course we don't have
to use that we can use some other
reference point we have our own calendar
systems we have the we have the Shaka
calendar we have the Vikram samat
calendar in which the year one is
something else it's not the BC ad
terminology right or we used to have the
saari calendar which when the Greeks
came to India around two
around what was it about 2,500 years ago
they said it was in existence for 6,000
years 6,000 plus years so we had our own
calendrical systems and we can use those
dates if we want but today I mean in
1947 there was the option that that
India could have adopted the Vikram
samat or the Shaka calendar but we chose
to adopt the Christian calendar our
so-called what founding fathers alleged
founding fathers they decided
that there are nations that have their
own calendarical systems even today the
Persians use a different calendar in
Persia they don't use the Christian
calendar but we we do so we have
chosen to use somebody else's infin
calendar we have chosen to say that they
are better than us and that's why these
terms exist so actually it's a good
question but that's just the way it is
you know
it's it's a sign of mental
colonization let the West use whatever
terms they want to use we don't have to
do that we are an older and greater
civilization but we have small people
who made decisions for us people who are
not worthy of being being called our
leaders who made these decisions for us
and that's why it has brought our
standards down in this country and
that's why that that these are so many
of the reasons put together why the
average Indian person has a tremendous
inferior complex without realizing it
the moment they see a person from the
West they they automatically feel that
person is better than and greater than
us you know I mean I'll tell you what
you
watch various YouTube videos of of
westerners white people going to Africa
and see how the Africans interact with
these white people they may go to a
pretty you know poor country like let's
say uh uh Mali or or or Ghana or
whatever tremendously poor country but
the Africans who interact with these
white people there they don't seem to
have an inferiority complex they don't
seem to automatically say oh you are a s
and we are we are we are we are
inferior if you see Afghans interacting
with people from Europe you don't see
the Afghans bowing down and you know
bowing and scraping to to Europeans but
every time you see the average Indian
interacting with the European the
average Indian is yes sir yes sir yes
sir yes Madam so Indians have this
tremendous in inferiority complex a
thousand years ago we weren't like this
but today we are like this it's because
of all of these things it's because of
all these little microscopic you know
four feet tall metaphorically that sort
of leaders who who became our allegedly
our leaders and made all these decisions
for us that you know create this
inferiority complex so it's it's
tremendously frustrating and that's why
don't like to take up these questions
I've taken them a lot before a lot of
this before but it's a good question and
I'm glad you asked it and I'm glad I
took it
today
okay uh B har nagar says how do you read
about Indian history as unlike other
histories Indian history changes with
with each author original texts findings
don't differ as much as modern authors
please suggest some authors I don't know
any authors uh Indian history if you
want to read Indian history you have to
read how do you read Indian history
look I have a bunch of books here
okay um not these here there's another
bookshelf over here which you're not
able to see and there are more
bookshelves here I have a tremendous
amount of books many of these books are
about Indian history I have a whole
section of books about Indian history uh
some of them are like are by people like
RC majumdar um some are by Foreign
authors and so on okay um El Basham the
the the wonder that was India uh and so
on you you will find that any single
book that you read that deals with
Indian history there are
distortions even the best meaning author
the the author who loved India even that
author's book you will find distortions
in in that book AR ma majumdar was a
firm believer in the Arian Invasion
Theory well he lived 100 years ago died
roughly 100 years ago I'm not sure which
when he died but the books were written
a long time ago decades ago almost 100
years ago so those books are going to be
outdated in in a lot of ways but even if
you take books
written more more recently most of these
books are going to say that the are the
so-called hypothetical Ed Invasion
happened that Indians are descendants of
Arians and dravidians which is utter
nonsense and other books will have other
flaws there is not a single book that I
can think of that doesn't have all of
these flaws and
distortions to some level and that's why
I never recommend any book on Indian
history I think I have a video on this
channel if you go back to the oldest
videos I think there is a set of book
recommendations and in those books also
you will find distortions so how do you
read
history most of you if you read you will
end up being misled and you will end up
absorbing
lies and I'll tell you what until 2015
2016 or thereabouts I was a firm
believer in the Aran invasion Theory so
how did this change it changed when so I
was on Twitter in back in the days it it
used to be called Twitter and on Twitter
I used to tweet about history and stuff
okay Back in the Day 2016 2017 around
that time and all the time people used
to tell me please debunk the RN
inversion Theory the r inversion theory
is a lie and I used to get irritated
with them that this is a scientific fact
all the authors are in agreement there
was an IR Invasion so why why can't you
accept facts why do you have to push
back against everything it used to
irritate me then for some reason one day
I said okay let me look into the actual
facts I'll not look at textbooks I'll
look at research
papers so I started looking at histo at
at uh Journal articles scientific
research papers in journals started
reading one by one going deeper and
deeper into the rabbit hole and after
spending like 100 hours or so in that I
was astonished I was shocked and I took
a complete 180° turn it became clear to
me that the Arn inversion theory is a
lie you
see so you if you really want to
understand history that's the approach
you to take you to spend countless hours
looking into original research not
opinions of authors that are available
in
textbooks but most people can't do that
most people don't even know how to read
a research
paper so for the average person the only
recourse you have is the best you can do
is to spend a few hours and read a
textbook or or a history book but that
is going to have opinions of the person
who wrote the and it it's going to have
the known and unknown biases of the
author who wrote the
book
right so that's why I prefer not to
recommend authors in
books uh there is no book that is
without distortions and biases so how do
I read it I I am aware aare of first of
all all the lies and all the
distortions that I'm aware of I'm sure
there there must be more that I'm not
aware of also and I'm aware of the
techniques that these people use to um
to mislead the the
reader so I when I read a book I know
exactly where that person is going to
lie and the moment I see it I know okay
there there you have it that's the lie
so there are sections entire sections
that are lies there are sections that
are distortions subtle dist distortions
on and so on so I over the years have
learned these techniques and these these
techniques that people have of lying and
and misleading the the audience so if
you if so I take a book I know okay some
parts are going to be lies but some part
is going to be of some some interest to
me so I'll read that that's how it is
that's how I read it but it's not
something everybody else can do
unfortunately so I don't know what to
say U if you really are interested in
history you to actually find time to
read research papers and even in
research favors you will have
distortions and lies so they will take
they will put one
sentence okay uh and which will be an
assumption without any basis and then
based on that sentence they will build a
whole edifice of Lies around
it so the Assumption they'll kind of
make is that you know U we found so and
so uh genetic lineage and so and so area
so it's associated with the origin of
the Indo Arian languages
how is it Associated but they'll just
put one sentence there and if it is not
challenged then they can build a whole
article around that based based on that
assumption the truth is that there is no
way to link DNA with a language but they
they're going to use that assumption so
even research papers are are full of
lies at times many of them especially
the ones that deal with the Aran
Invasion thing and all that and that's
just the way it
is so I cannot suggest
authors because if I suggest authors and
you'll read them and then you'll come
back and and point fingers at me that
you suggested this author and that
author has made this statement and how
dare you suggest this I get a lot of
that that's why I don't I don't
recommend any
authors Su says Trump announced the f47
linking it to two years of US tech
development can could this be tried tied
to U for sightings uh soon China's j35 6
generation jet was spot why is the US
Open China stay quiet no one's open
everybody lies everybody hides things
this F f47 that's been announced
recently it's been flying for more than
five
years okay that aircraft that prototype
has been flying for more than five
years maybe more maybe there are more
prototypes and maybe this theyve
announced the f47 but maybe there's an
f57 somewhere or f67 somewhere and those
prototypes are also flying around and
they will not be announced in the next
20 years perhaps so there's a lot of uh
lot of experimental aircraft
developmental aircraft prototypes that
are always being tested at any given
point in time especially in a country
like the
US and of course people if they cite
that they will say they will believe
it's a UFO because it is not uh any
known aircraft design that is known in
the public domain and it may have
properties that are different from
regular
aircraft uh so yeah it it certainly can
be tied to year for sightings now the
j35 6th generation jet was spotted no it
was not spotted the Chinese allowed it
to be spotted they announced the
existence of this sixth generation
Jet right so it was not an accidental
spotting that somebody made a discovery
of something that the Chinese have not
announced the Chinese announced it
um the US how do you know the US is open
I mean the past 5 years they could have
announced the f47 they did not right for
5 years they were quiet they were
secretive about it now that it's
officially in development and they
they've chosen to announce it but I
assure you there's a whole bunch of
experimental aircraft that are being
developed right now that they have not
announced to you so just because they
announced one thing how do you assume
that they are open how can you be so
gullible please please be a little more
mature
just because they announced one thing
doesn't mean they are open there's 99
other things they're not announcing to
you when they announced the existence of
stealth aircraft during the Gulf War era
uh that stealth bomber of that time was
flying for 20 years but they had not not
announced it they had kept it secret for
like 20 years they started developing
stealth technology in the
1970s but they did not announce it until
uh the 1990s so they keep a lot of stuff
secret they keep it secret for decades
who says they are open just because they
announc one thing doesn't mean they're
open it's just that they're doing it
strategically to make it look like you
know to to mislead
people okay I announced this see I'm
open what about the other 99 things
you're not announcing sh don't talk
about
that that's the kind of thing they
always do you know Freedom democracy and
human rights they are the worst
violators of Freedom democracy and human
rights but through propaganda they make
it look like they are the the world's
leading power that supports democracy
freedom and human rights so it's not
like that please please be a little more
mature than this come
on
everybody has things to hide and you
should
okay Sergeant skyin says do you think
India's sovereignty has been compromised
is China on the rise or decline
do you think India's do I think India's
sovereignty has been
compromised we are not a technologically
Sovereign Nation please understand that
technologically look we are talking
right now I am communicating with you
all taking your questions right now in
real time
right am I doing this because of Indian
technology I'm not right I'm using an
American platform to do this the if this
plat form and all these platforms
disappear we Indians will have no way to
communicate with with each
other social media you know what it's
done it has given the average Indian
person a voice for the first time in a
thousand years and we are all able to
communicate with each other in real time
all of us wherever we are in India and
in the world because of these platforms
these social media
platforms all of these platforms are
American
platforms if these platforms disappear
here we are no we will have no idea no
way of staying in touch with with each
other right so do you think we are
technologically Sovereign we're not
technologically we are not a Sovereign
Nation and I think the government of
India should do this on a war footing to
have our own
platforms as a backup at
least so that in case the Western
platforms disappear for whatever reason
we Indians can stay in touch with each
other I think it's it's important for us
as a nation to remain in touch with with
each other no matter what happens to be
able to communicate with each other in
real time it's happened only because of
the West it's not happened because of
India Indian it's not happening because
of Indian companies or Indian
government so India is not a
technologically Sovereign
Nation not at all and it that is an area
of great
concern it doesn't seem to be something
that is high on our list of priorities
that the the fact that we are
technologically not sovereign are we uh
territorially Sovereign yeah we are
territorially sovereign more or less
some parts of our territory are in
foreign control obviously we know that
PO Gil balistan Ain and so on yeah
that's that's an issue certainly uh
there is the issue of Manipur a whole
few hundred thousand foreigners are
squatting on Indian Territory in Manipur
and oppressing the the natives that's an
issue so there are some gray areas which
are of great concern there is the the
the fact that there's 100 million
bangladeshis on Indian Territory that's
an area of great concern and that
doesn't seem to be once again on a very
high on the list of priorities that we
need to get rid of them as soon as
possible so yeah there are there are
definitely issues but overall if you
look at the big picture macro
perspective you know 10,000 meter level
India is one of the four Sovereign
Nations overall but yes you you raise
good questions you raise good questions
here here and there are certainly areas
of concern is China on the rise or
decline technologically China is on the
rise technologically China is the only
nation that can compete with the US
almost neck to neck so that's way China
is on the rise uh China has no real
threat apart from the US and perhaps to
some extent Russia uh India is not
really a threat for China India can
defend itself but India is not a threat
for China India is not going to China is
not afraid that India will tomorrow you
know suddenly March upon Chinese
territory and take away Tibet or
whatever that's not a fear the Chinese
have it's not a realistic fear uh so
China only has the us as a threat and to
some extent perhaps Russia but they are
managing Russia right now uh so
technologically they are very much on
the rise demographically they are in
Decline right now and that's a big issue
area of concern for them because by 2100
their population will be about half of
what it is today and the the population
will be the average age will be about in
the 60s which is area of great concern
but they're hoping that they can use Ai
and Robotics to offset that issue and so
on we'll see about that but a nation has
to be young in order to be vigorous in
energetic your population ideally should
be in its 20s or 30s the average age the
median age of a population should
ideally be in the early 30s or late 20s
that's that's ideally what you want in
India it's about 33 34 which is an area
of concern in China it's already higher
than
that so uh there are issues in China
there's a demographic collapse that's uh
impending which is not an urgent issue
but a very big issue long term but
technologically it's on the rise
militarily it's untested the last
military engagement of any kind they had
serious engagement was in 1979 when they
had a war with Vietnam which they lost
but that's in 79 today is 2025 a long
time ago and there was another clash in
1987 between India and China which India
won but it was a very major minor thing
compared to the Vietnam the war that
China had with Vietnam they tried to
invade Vietnam so China's military is
untested but they their military is very
powerful at least on paper their Navy is
very powerful at least on paper
numerically it's the largest Navy in the
world they and you what is the real
measure of a Navy's power it's not how
many ships you deploy at Sea the only
measure of a Navy's Firepower
or lethality is how many missiles you
can deploy at se at any given point in
time let's say I have a Navy that can
deploy a 100 ships today right
now and each ship has one missile so my
lethality is 100 missiles let's say your
Navy has 20 ships and each ship has five
missiles so you also are deploying 100
missiles so your 20 ships are equal to
my 100 ships because you have 100
missiles that you deploy and I have 100
missiles that you deploy if the Chinese
can deploy 200 ships and each ship has
missiles 200 that's about 6,000 missiles
they're deploying that's a whole
different scale of Firepower so the only
measure of a Navy's strength is how many
missiles they are able to deploy at any
given point in time on
average and the Chinese I think are
quite up there with the Americans maybe
even higher than Americans and the
question is how many can we
deploy how many missiles are we
deploying on a on a routine basis at
see our best
destroyers have about 32 or 36 missiles
I think or 32 perhaps you know those VLS
tubes and all that I think it's a big
area of concern we need to have higher
missile deployment per ship not sure
what the thought process is but yeah
there are there are concerns anyhow
that's that's yeah that's the answer to
your
question okay let's see some more
question Anonymous scientist says have
you watched Lex fredman's podcast with
Mr Modi what are your views why did
Trump share that podcast I haven't seen
the podcast I I don't watch podcasts I
don't have the time for that um and and
I know Mr modi's views and yeah I
haven't watched it I haven't even
watched maybe 30 second clip here and
there something so I haven't watched it
I don't have any about it why did Trump
share the podcast because Mr Modi must
have said nice things about Mr
Trump that's what I would say uh
yeah ragav Aurora says for bat to become
a real hard power what does it need to
do is there any other missile technology
or more power that nuclear missiles that
can be developed to challenge the world
finger red number one okay for bat to
become a hard power what does it need to
do there are internal issues it needs to
address and external issues needs to
address the biggest issues are are
internal for bhat to become a real hard
power it has to become more efficient
power internally which means all the red
tape all the bloat all the inertia needs
to be cut out this this you know the
government is is like an employment
generation scheme for bureaucrats and
bureaucrats they are in you know once
you become a bureaucrat you have a job
for life no matter what you do whether
you perform you don't perform and that's
a very big issue we need to have a much
leaner meaning and more efficient
bureaucracy first of all uh there is a
tremendous amount of alleged alleged
corruption in India it is alleged that
India operates the governance system
allegedly entirely operates allegedly on
corruption allegedly okay it is alleged
that way so that needs to be cut out uh
every institution is
allegedly you know issues there are
issues within it I think the biggest
issue within India allegedly is alleged
corruption okay
I think that's a number one issue in
India and if if you cut out even 50% of
that India will become a different kind
of
Beast so that's number one thing India
needs to address the alleged corruption
that is all over the alleged Place
allegedly uh secondly what does India
need to do uh India needs to change its
system of governance or or it's its
system of democracy we need to have
presidential system end of story this
parliamentary democracy came out of a
small island in the Atlantic Ocean
called England
it's suitable for a small island country
it's not suitable for for a gigantic
subcontinent sized Nation we need to
have a presidential
system end of story parliamentary
democracy Westman style democracy is not
working for
India we need a presidential system
which is an interim step in towards
something
else and then we need to end all these
reservations and all based on cast
enough of reservations based on cast if
you want reservations fine give
reservations to People based on their
financial condition not based on
cast and reservations should be only up
to Standard 12 or college or whatever
you cannot have reservations and jobs
and reservations and everything there
needs to be Merit in the country without
meritocracy country cannot you know
there's no chance it will do well in in
in the long term and then what do we
need to do to be a hard
power
um India should focus on the on the Navy
India has historically been a maritime
power historically and today we are
blindly eeping other countries we need
to become a maritime power we have this
god- gifted position geographical
position that every other power envies
look at the map look at the map look at
where we are sitting we we dominate the
Indian Ocean region we are in a position
to dominate the whole area and and elbow
everybody else out if we want but to do
that we need a massive Navy and not
those godamn aircraft
carriers I know these are prestigious
gigantic ships but we don't need those
we need sharks not elephants we need a
large number of submarines maybe a 100
submarines of various kinds and we need
maybe 300 surface vessels on top of
having 100 submarines that's what we
need we need to have a constant Indian
presence all across the Indian Ocean
region enough of these slogans like
which say that the Indian Ocean is a
strategic backyard a slogan is not
making going to make you a power you
need to have visible presence wherever
wherever you go in the Indian Ocean
right now if you're are a friendship or
an American ship or any ship traveling
the Indian Ocean do you see any Indian
presence anywhere you don't
you don't so if you want to become a
hard power you need to have that you we
need to have a clear focus on Navy we
need to have at least 100 submarines of
various kinds enough of these godamn
aircraft
carriers okay and we need to focus on
distributed
lethality I don't I am perfectly okay
with smaller
ships you know the deadliest ship one of
the deadliest kind of ships is actually
a boat missile boat
boat a missile boat is a small vessel on
which you can have three missiles at a
time and that little ship which may cost
maybe $10 million can destroy ships
costing hundreds of million dollars so
we need to think in that manner we need
an agile Navy we need an unconventional
Navy and you know we can do a lot with
less money if you
want so we need to do that we need to
become so there's the Naval aspect we
need to
obviously have our own jet engines we
need to have drone technology we need to
really have much more military muscle to
flex than we have right now and we need
to become a technological Powerhouse
right now we we are a second rate
technological power technologically we
are not even Sovereign when it comes to
social media and all that and
technologically we are always trying to
do what others have done 20 30 years ago
that's what Dro Etc does except for
missiles it's only in missile technology
that we are a world
leader India has the best missile
systems in the world right now I'm sure
we have icbms that can reach anywhere in
the world we don't talk about that so in
missiles we are the best but we need to
be the best in everything else as well
so there's a lot we can do so that's we
to what we have to focus
on right
um crazy bra says what's up with our
neighbors well which neighbors are you
referring to there's a lot of neighbors
that we have uh let's take a look at the
map and we'll talk about some of our
neighbors how how about we do that yeah
what's up with our neighbors so the
first neighbor everybody thinks of when
we talk about our neighbors is
Pakistan West Pakistan so what's
happening in West Pakistan things are
never well in West Pakistan West
Pakistan is always on the brink of
collapse but because of money that flows
in from the US right now west Pakistan
will continue to exist as long the as
the Americans uh find it useful for West
Pakistan to exist uh so things are not
well there there's obviously U issues
baluchistan is a big issue uh there's a
lot of uh unrest in baluchistan the
Pakistani military is is facing setback
after setback in baluchistan there
that's an issue when it comes to uh the
K pakun region once again it's not
really Pakistani Sovereign territory the
Taliban rules there right that's an
issue for Pakistan for West Pakistan um
and so on so West Pakistan is a nation
that's always like one foot in the grave
U always on the on the brink of
bankruptcy all it's a it's an almost
failed state but not quite because of
Western support that's the deal with
West Pakistan Afghanistan is doing okay
uh it is ruled by the Taliban the
Taliban is to some extent a US proxy to
some extent they have an understanding
with the US the Doha agreement which had
secret Clauses which we not aware of but
um it is alleged by very reputable
sources that uh the Taliban government
is is paid a weekly sement of between
$50 to100 million in cash by the
Americans uh that's to to keep their end
of the bargain so what did what the
Taliban do is they keep China out of the
region
essentially that that's essentially what
it is so the the the the uh what is it
the one belt one road initiative uh
built and Road initiative that thing
that is not going through Afghanistan
that's what the Chinese wanted so
Afghanistan is kind of doing okay the
other na Nations Tajikistan I don't
think indiaan Indians even regard
Tajikistan as a neighbor it's right next
door it's right next door but Indians
don't even think know about Tajikistan
Tajikistan is doing okay nothing special
happening there um there is that then
the other neighbors Tibet China well
pretty stable no big issues there Nepal
there seems to be uh a ground swell of
support for the uh nepales monarchy for
the for the uh deposed King Shri
ganendra G so we'll see what happens
about that people are sick and tired of
the corrupt politicians the the the
nepales politicians and they would like
to see a Return of the King and a return
of the Nepal is monarchy there's more
and more support for that so we'll see
about that Bhutan I will not speak about
it right
now we'll see about that uh East
Pakistan or Bangladesh is not doing well
they are
it's the nation is currently run by the
by the military they have a puppet at
the top called Muhammad Yus the the
great Noble late who is a US proxy um
and East Pakistan is also a a US asset
now Sri Lanka is is doing okay malis are
doing okay uh Indonesia is fine
Indonesia and India's relations are good
most Indians don't even think of
Indonesia as our neighbor well here's
here's some news for you the between
Indonesia and India is about 200
kilometers at most it's just 200
kilometers away from India and yet
Indians don't think of Indonesia as
neighbor so weird another neighbor is
Thailand Okay if you look at the
distance from India to Thailand it's
about let's say 500 kilometers okay so
even Thailand is a neighbor that we are
not aware of and Thailand is also doing
okay the area of concern is Myanmar
Burma where there's a civil war that's
that's raging
uh and uh there is this big issue
project K cookie land for Christ that
the Americans had Unleashed and it's
still going on and millions not Millions
but hundreds of thousands of of these
cookie infiltrators have entered Manipur
and that is a big issue for
India so yeah there are parts of Manipur
that are under foreign control right now
yeah and there are lots of issues over
there which I will not go into into
detail but yeah so overall that's the
situation in the subcontinent extended
subcontinent region if you talk about
Iran well Iran Etc is also there are
there are there a whole other set of
issues when it comes to the West Asia
region Iran is kind of between the
subcontinent and West Asia uh
historically culturally part of the
subcontinent extended region but
geographically now it's right now it's
seen as part of West Asia and so on so
yeah that's what's the deal with our
neighbors right
now all right
um
um Prashant says what are your views on
sers atheism and why do Indian people
have a stereotype that a non-believer
can't rece respect is badia culture
akatan sanism I look I haven't I don't
know much about Mr sarer there are many
historical figures that I've not studied
and I'm not aware of
like for example Dr ambedkar I have not
studied Dr edar edar at all I haven't
read any of his books any of his
writings I haven't read any book about
him I have no idea about Mr edar Dr edar
similarly Mr when it comes to Mr sarar
uh I haven't read anything about him I
obviously have heard about him I'm aware
of the general context and his his
relevance in industry and so on but I
don't know much in detail I know that
he's one of the freedom fighters who who
should get a great deal more credit than
what he's given and a lot of people hate
him right and the people who generally
hate him are the people who are
typically the lefties and stuff right so
yeah I obviously I'm aware of that what
do I what are My Views about sers
atheism I don't care about his atheism
uh okay so I've heard that he was an
atheist so what you can be an atheist
and a Hindu at the same time you can be
of course you don't have to believe in
God to love your culture
civilization right look even if you take
the religious the the Divine aspect out
of what we call sanatan Dharma religion
let's take the Divine aspect out of it
because let's say you don't believe in
God but you still if you if you even if
you take the Divine aspect out of
sanatan Dharma you have the the the the
values and
morality which make a lot of sense even
if you're an
atheist and it's the best system of
morality and in values in the
world right so you can be an atheist and
still love your culture and and and love
your civilization so and when it comes
to Hindu Dharma and the various
philosophical schools of thought I have
a video on that very brief video five
minute long if you look at the
philosophical schools of thought there
are atheistic schools of thought in
zatan Dharma I mean b the the B the
school of thought
Buddha D it's part of the dharmic
umbrella and it's kind of
atheistic kind of they don't believe in
God they some say that there is no there
is no belief in the soul either which is
a point of
contention if you look at J well there
is no Divinity in in in J DH either
there's no God in J DH but there is the
existence of the
Soul Atma when you look at the charvaka
school of thought it's a purely
materialistic school of thought
completely atheistic and yet it's part
of sanatan Dharma right so you can very
much be an atheist and be a dharmic
person so I it makes no difference to me
whether Mr sarer was a atheist or a
theist it makes no difference to me
whatsoever he he fought for our
civilization our culture our nation and
that's that's all that I care about so
that's why I have the greatest of
respect for him and obviously he
suffered a lot for his beliefs and and
for
for um the cause that he fought for so
respect for that what
else
okay um CH arising says what are your
thoughts on the baluchistan movement
since Pakistan Army usually are us
leading do you think the Bulan movement
will break up Pakistan or is this for
deep state to put pressure on the
Pakistan government okay okay let's look
at the balistan issue from uh
geographical perspective let's look at
the map here we have the map so now
baluchistan what is baluchistan if you
think of baluchistan today if most
Indians think of baluchistan they'll
think of the western part of Pakistan
the capital of baluchistan is said to be
qua okay it's the major city it's it's
probably the largest province in
Pakistan uh if
I baluchistan
Pakistan so it it won't give you Google
Maps will not show you a geographical
delimitation of baluchistan but it's
this region overall but the actual
baluchistan historical baluchistan half
of it is in Iran
today you see chabahar if you zoom in
here chabahar is a port in the Iranian
part of
baluchistan I would even say that places
like zahedan are part of Iranian
baluchistan see San and baluchistan
Province and I would say even probably
no okay B Abbas is part of part of horos
an Province Min minab Etc jirof is
Kirman Province and so on zahedan is
definitely San bistan Iran Shahar is San
bistan so the point is about half of
historical bistan is currently in
Iran okay so now if you want India to
support the baluchistan Freedom Movement
it this complicates things the fact that
half of baluchistan is in Iran if you
want to if you say that I want
baluchistan to be independent it's going
to raise concerns in Iran because they
have half of baluchistan and the people
in Iran and bistan are also baluchi
people they're not
Persians okay they are more Indian and
Persian of course Persians and Indians
are also long story anyway uh so that is
one thing that complicates the matters
if if you want to support the bistan
independence movement so then you to
explicitly said the state that I am
talking about Pakistani baluchistan or
or the region of
kalat so historically there was a state
called kalat there was a Khan of kalat
and in 47 or something the Khan of kalat
had signed the instrument of accession
to India he wanted kalat to be a part of
India and he sent the instrument of
accession signed to Shri jawahar neuj
who rejected it because Shri neuj did
not want India to be larger and more
more powerful country for well he was a
magnificent man probably definitely way
more intelligent than us so we can't
understand what he's to you know the the
depths of his intellect there must be
good reasons for whatever he did I'm not
sure so the point is
this uh if you want to support the
bistan independence movement you to say
that it's only the Pakistani baluchistan
or the kalat region whose Independence
we are supporting now Pakistan Army
obviously it's us funded so obviously
they they
the the yeah we know that the Pakistan
Army is US funded Pakistan is a US wasal
state after the after 2022 when there
was a coup that outed Imran Khan so will
the baluchistan independence movement
break up break up Pakistan no it won't
not not at this point in time right now
the Pakistani military is too powerful
and the baloi uh Freedom Fighters don't
have sufficient resources to to defeat
the Pakistani military it's like Ukraine
you know let's let's compare with the
Ukraine situation see Ukraine what are
the options Ukraine has right now in the
war Russia started the military
operation in 2022 February right
February
2022 today is uh what is it March 2025
it's been three years three years plus
what options does does Ukraine have for
ending the war option one defeat Russia
thoroughly complete military defeat from
Russia then the war ends or
or you agree to a SE fire on Russian
terms the third option is you keep the
war going for another three years and
Ukraine gets completely destroyed as a
consequence the best solution is either
to defeat Russia if you can or accept
ceasefire on Russian terms they can't
defeat Russia so you accept a ceasefire
similarly right now if you look at the
baluchistan situation The baluchistan
Liberation Army isn't powerful enough to
defeat the Pakistani military right now
and a ceasefire is not in know
then it doesn't work for them because
they are under military occupation for
the past 70 plus years so they'll keep
on fighting this
Insurgency and that's a situation so
it's going to keep keep the pressure on
Pakistan going on and uh is this the
Deep State that's behind this well I
don't know I don't know who's behind
this uh I'm sure the baloi independence
movement has
multiple supporters from perhaps outside
I I can assure you that India is not
behind this India doesn't participate in
any such activities India itself has
suffered from a lot of non-state actor
activities in the past coming across the
border from Pakistan and so on so we
don't do these things okay but I'm sure
there are many supporters non non-state
supporters of baluchistan so I think
it's is going to go on I don't think
Pakistan will break up anytime very
soon
right all
right Shri balam Putin G says do you
have nice words for the UK and England
you know what do I think about the UK
and England um they had beautiful
culture the original culture of the UK
and England the original Celtic culture
was
beautiful it was a polytheistic culture
it's the pre-christian culture beautiful
um even the Anglo-Saxon culture the
pre-christian culture was beautiful but
the Celtic culture was even better the
music if you look at if you if you
listen to Celtic music for example folk
music which has Celtic origin in the UK
and
England from that origin is in the UK
England that region even Scottish Irish
music it's incredibly beautiful they
have something called the Celtic harp
the harp overall and so
on
and um what's the guy's name I forget
the musicians name uh there are many
musician who have explored Celtic
um you know fusing Celtic music with
other kinds of music for example lead
Zeppelin lead Zeppelin we most people
think of Le Zeppelin as a hard rock band
but lead Zeppelin at least 40% of the
music is acoustic non-electric okay and
lot of lot lot of the music is folk
music and it's not very well known that
LE Zeppelin came to India Mumbai Bombay
it was then called in the 1970s and
recorded a whole uh session album
uh with local
musicians and if you listen to the
bootleg recordings you can see it's so
natural to that these these two styles
of music fuse together so
naturally and the the folk influences in
leip music are Celtic folk influences um
dve Graham was a musician I think he has
passed away but in the 60s 50s and 60s
he started experimenting fusing Celtic
music with Indian music and he found
that it's it's just a natural
combination that just works naturally
well
together um Indian instruments like the
T sitar Etc and Celtic music just
naturally work together so there is a
very ancient connection between the
cultures of India and the Celtic and
Celtic culture of Ireland Scotland and
and pre pre-christian
England and you know so their culture
used to be beautiful now has been
destroyed first of all by the
Anglo-Saxons the angloa Saxons well it's
just Invasion that invasions happen but
yeah the polytheistic culture was
beautiful which was destroyed by the
Christians and that's that's
um that's that's sad some of it still
exists it's it's a subsurface current
kind of thing so yeah the music is
beautiful okay and what else can I say
nice things about England UK I'm pretty
fond of Scotland Ireland very nice
people nice landscape you know you can
have four seasons in one day and I would
say it's a great place to visit you know
very there's a lot of natural beauty
there very nice culture um I like the
languages the the Scottish G Scottish
language the Irish GIC language and so
on even the Welsh
language there's there's a lot of
languages in there that have all been
suppressed by the English language the
English are a very hegemonic people and
they've done a lot of harm to the local
cultures actually so there's a lot of
good in England too of course England
has been a force of great Destruction
for us here in India and so on and today
one kind of feels that they are reaping
the fruits of what they sowed here
because today there's a
whole immigration issue in England they
have selectively brought in certain
kinds of immigrants from the
subcontinent not indians but the
Pakistani flavor of immigrants Pakistani
Bangladesh's and they are now creating
Havoc uh in England so yeah it's sad you
know it kind of makes me sad at a
certain level to see that but you reap
what you s I would
say okay so
yeah
um okay bries SK says recently there was
a parents teacher meeting okay good and
a lecturer told students that you should
not make money before you get graduated
or you get a
degree
why why should you not make
money you should start making money at
the earliest in your life if you can
start making money by by the time you're
13 do
it you can do some part-time work
or why shouldn't you make
money and what's the point of these
degrees what you need is skills
but the education system is such that
without a piece of paper that says that
you have got this degree you will not
get a job and so on the whole system is
rotten and corrupt you know and these
teachers they these people they are the
real stakeholders of the system they are
the ones who benefit the most and if you
start making money before you get a
degree then why then you will say say to
yourself why do I need the degree I
already I'm already making good money so
they want you to be in a situation where
you have to depend on these
degrees and without these pieces of
paper these people have the power to
withhold from you without this pieces of
paper you have no
future because if you have money then
you have freedom right and if you are
making money by the time you 16 17 18
then you are free already and you have
options and they don't need a degree so
these
teachers they are not your gurus they
are service
providers they don't deserve the respect
that a genuine Guru deserves to have you
know this people are service providers
they will stop teaching you the moment
you stop paying them their monthly fees
or
whatever uh and and it is in their
interest for you to have less options
and it is in see these degrees this
paper these pieces of paper that they
have the power to give to you or
withhold from you that's a form of
blackmail they have or you so that's why
they will want you to believe that
unless until you get the degree you
should not make any money I will tell
you the
opposite if you are 13 years old if
you're 14 15 16 whatever age you are
yeah sure study for your degree I I
think it's a waste of time but okay
study for your degree but start
exploring ways of making money on your
own without having a job today you can
make money from your
home if you are computer literate if you
have other kinds of skills you can start
making money from your home from your
home without having a job a fixed job
you can do that there are so many ways
of doing it so I think if you are a
youngster you should start exploring
these things and the ideal situation is
that by the time you're 18 you should
have a salary of your own maybe ideally
a few lack of rupees a month at least a
few 10 20,000 rupees a
month and then you will realize that
these once you have that you know the
purpose of life is to have freedom it's
to have skills that benefit Society to
make money from those skills and that
that money gives you freedom to do
whatever you want that's and as long as
you contributing to society and you have
a good good place in society you are
respected and you respect everybody else
you're canot be reasonably happy in life
and that's the whole purpose of existing
for most people isn't
it and these degrees are used to be a
pathway towards that that the degree
says that you have spend your time and
paid your dues and you are you are a
reasonably well qualified person and
then that's so that companies can hire
you but today you know you don't really
need that so my point is don't listen to
these teachers they they are talking
they are saying this because it benefits
them not not because it benefits you you
should make money at the earliest you
should start making money at the
earliest you should learn at the
earliest age how to make money different
ways of making money all legal and good
ways of making money but there are lots
of good and legal ways of making money
and you don't need to be 18 or 24 or 25
to be to make money you can start doing
that at age of 15 if you want so do
that and once you do that you will
realize these degrees are worthless all
worthless
um uh okay this is this is a interaction
between people okay that's fine uh let's
see some other questions
um okay Gob says can India stop
concentrating on advanced fighter Jets
and focus on stealth missiles and drones
to catch up and even dominate The Domain
uh I think India should do multiple
things in parallel we have the resources
and the money to work on multiple things
at the same time uh you don't have to
just focus on one thing and stop
focusing on everything else doesn't
matter so my point is I I I understand
what you're saying here and why you're
saying this okay first of all yeah
fighter jets fighter planes are kind of
older
technology today if you have drones
then you can overwhelm the battlefield
without the use of a fighter plane right
yes and if you have long range missiles
that are very hard to detect and very
hard to take down then once again you
don't need fighter planes yes true very
true so we need to focus on these
Technologies definitely we do yeah now
when it comes to missiles we have some
of the best missile systems offensive
and defensive in the
world um yeah we need better we need to
keep working on better mile systems so
let's say we have the Brahma such a
supersonic missile 10 years ago it was
the best missile in the world today not
quite so it's no longer the fastest
missile of the deadliest missile in the
world it's still a very deadly missile
sure but we need to have a Hypersonic
and a super Hypersonic
brahos uh if you look at the Russian
missiles like the kinal the ton Etc I
think the siron is Mark 9 or Mark 10
that's ridiculously fast brahos is m 2
come on it's time to move on so uh we
need to keep on improving our missile
systems improving and increasing the
deadliness The lethality definitely we
need to concent on that we need to
definitely focus a lot on
drones drones can you know with drones
you can overwhelm the battlefield
without sending a single soldier without
the use of without needing uh fighter
planes or whatever the thing about
drones please understand drones don't
have long legs thus far I cannot send a
swarm of 2,000 drones 2,000 kilm away I
can send a swarm of 2,000 drones 100
kilometers away maybe but drones don't
have those long legs to go 2,000 3,000
kilometers away I can't deploy them that
far to deploy them that far I need to
First go closer to the
battlefield maybe I can take a ship or
something there and then deplo deploy
the drones from from there so drones are
very good technology very useful can be
very deadly but right now it has
limitations certain limitations I'm sure
the limitations will also be overcome
eventually but let's say you want to
send an army of drones a swarm of
thousand 2,000 5,000 drones 2,000
kilometers away you're going to go have
you're going to have to go over other
people's territory perhaps and these
drones aren't supersonic
drones and they could be intercepted as
also so there are issues there are
issues understand that uh so drones
can't solve every problem some
problems they can be solved with
missiles some problems can be solved
with drones some problems can be solved
with fighter planes and so on so forth
some problems need strategic
bombers and so
on so my point is we need to have every
single kind of
technology so we should not stop
concentrating on advanced fighter jets
absolutely not we should develop better
and better fighter planes we should at
the same time develop better and better
missiles and we should at the same time
develop better and better drones we
should also at the same time de develop
better submarines develop better
underwater
drones develop
better destroyers and so on everything
needs to be worked on simultaneously you
can't stop concentrating on one thing
one thing
I would say don't even stop
concentrating on aircraft carriers we
have I don't know two two at least right
now so keep those two so that the the
Navy knows how to operate aircraft
carriers and maybe 20 30 years in 20 30
years time we may need we may be in a
position with that we now need aircraft
carriers right now we should not build
more but maybe in 30 years when we are a
much larger power more powerful Nation
we may need a few so at that time if we
already have the ongoing capability of
using n career then we can develop more
and we want to start training Soldiers
and Sailors from scratch again so you
should not stop concentrating on
anything not you can't just give up on a
technology even if the technology is old
it still has some use understand that
all
right
okay
um H says what I thoughts in Kar some
people say it's still time other people
I have no idea I have absolutely no idea
on
Kar okay so yeah I'm the wrong person to
ask questions about that no idea
whatsoever prakar Gupta says thousands
of pages of J JFK killing files are
released and he talks about CIA role and
assassination your views on the files um
I haven't read a single one of the files
when you dump a few thousand pages of
files what you're doing is you're
increasing the number the amount of
noise
a lot of these files you will see that
there are redactions you know black
stripes across the the the text which
omits you know which censors some of the
text and most of it is just procedural
stuff most of it is just noise and and
random uh non-important stuff and
uh I hear look there are various AI
systems that have gone through all the
files and once again there are no huge
big Revelations what CIA
role if you are you know after reading
all the files if you ask the question
who killed JFK you still don't have the
answer there are hints of the CIA
involved men there are questions about
where was George
George um the George Bush senior at the
time he apparently doesn't remember
where he was that day and so
on which agencies were involved we still
have
hints we still don't know who was behind
The Killing so My Views are what's my
view on this my view is that they they
still hiding what really
happened
look here's what we need to know how
many people were there who shot at JFK
the Warren Commission report the
official report until today it says that
JFK was shot from
behind Okay from a building up there
maybe 9th 10th whatever don't remember
right now but from behind so it means
the bullet came from behind and hit him
from the back in the back of the head if
you watch the zaper
film you will see that his head goes
back like that you can see it blows up
from here which means the shot was fired
from above from from front not from
behind so the warrant commission is
lying the official statement the
official uh position of the government
has been a lie for decades it's clear is
clear as day watch the zap rer film it's
available on YouTube I don't play it
here right now but it's it's clear that
he was shot from the front he was see he
was shot in the throat first of all he's
grabbing his throat and his wife is
looking at what happened and then while
she's looking at him he's again shot in
the front in the forehead his his
forehead blows up like that and his head
is is you
know it is jolted backwards it's clear
the shot from the front so at least two
bullet WS are there minimum two so the
question first of all is how many
shooters were there second question is
what are the identities of the shooters
clearly that guy I forget the name not
John Ruben what ruby did I say
something Jack Ruby right not Jack Ruby
uh Oswald Lee Harvey
Oswald it looks like he wasn't the guy
he in his own words was just a pathy and
he was shot by a guy called Jack Ruby
Ruby was it Ruby or something
else Ruby let's say and Ruby also dies
later
so it all conveniently was wrapped up
the question is who were the shooters
the actual Shooters and who were they
working for what was the chain of
command none of the questions are
addressed so what's the point of these
thousands of pages of JFK killing files
it's JFK noise it's noise around the
issue they haven't released the truth so
that's my view on it it's it's you know
they making it look like they they
making some progress and being more
transparent but actually they're doing
nothing of the sort there's no
transparency
whatsoever
okay huh all right all right
um let's see what other questions do we
have
um did do
say if Bob lazzar's testimony is true
then how will anti-gravity and look I
don't know what bobazar I don't know
what his testimony does anti-gravity
exist look I have some kind of
understanding of physics okay I have a
little bit of understanding of physics
as far as I know there is no no
anti-gravity theory of anti-gravity uh
yeah you can theoretically have time
travel theoretically you can
theoretically you can have uh certain
things like that according to the
Einstein equations of General general
relativity but how will anti-gravity
annihilate economy trade space Quantum
technology time magic war
machines
uh and
look I I first of all I don't know what
Lazar has said or what he has not said
I've not watched any of the interviews
or read any of the stuff uh secondly if
if he's claiming anti-gravity exists
show me evidence of it existing and show
me the the physics behind it show me the
equations that tell you that
anti-gravity
exists uh so
yeah I'm I'm super skeptical and I I'm
not sure if this is true that's what I
can say sorry I'm not able to answer
your question in a satisfactory way
because uh the premise itself is
unsatisfactory you know the claim the
claim not your not what you're saying
but the
claim Ananda bishwas says in the podcast
with Lex fredman uh Prime Minister Modi
said without India AI is in incomplete
what do I make of the statement I make
nothing of the statement how is AI look
I first of all I have not seen the
interview secondly I know I'm not sure
what statement he has actually made and
what are my views on this AI will exist
without with or without India India is a
late entrant in the field I'm not sure
if we have even started working on an AI
system I don't know of any private
company that's working on AI I think um
Mr Shar Vu of of Zoho is working on AI
it may take time for that to fructify I
believe that the government of India
said that we're going to have an LM of
Our Own by the end of the year big deal
just because everybody has an LM we
should also have ANM what's the point of
that what are we going to do with AI
so I don't know see first of all I
haven't seen the interview secondly I'm
not sure what statement was made my
point is AI is AI is already here India
is way
behind India is always trying to catch
up with what people have done in the
past so in lots of Technologies India is
trying to do what people did 2030 years
ago and that seems to be the same
situation in the case of AI I hope that
uh I am wrong and the government of
India actually does take a serious
initiative and in the next two three
years makes India a leading nation in
the in AI so if if we are serious it can
happen if Mr Modi is serious if the
government of India is serious I'm sure
we can catch up with the US and China in
the next 2 three years it's going to be
a hell of a lot of work to do it's
possible but thus far I only hear
slogans and
words and I I think everybody is tired
of
slogans okay everyone's tired of slogans
I think the whole country is tired of
slogans there's been a lot of
slogans you know make it happen and then
we'll
see make it happen and then we will see
that's what I can
say uh do you think India is a failed
state is what M Mr Watson says I don't
think India as of real estate no it's
not it's
not W Kumar Sharma says please end those
two repeated live stream it's weird
listen sir if you don't want to watch it
don't watch it no one's forcing you to
watch it
right is is it is it creating a problem
in your life in some
way I have two live streams going on on
Loop old episodes if people want to
watch they can watch because there are
lots of questions that people ask that
have been answered in the past so you
know if you have some time you nothing
to do watch half an hour of of an older
live stream it may help you in some way
if if you don't want to watch it sir
please don't watch it it's not creating
any problem in your life if you feel
it's weird don't watch it no one's
forcing you to watch it but why do you
want me to end it I'm going to start two
more
now come on
man all right let's see what else do we
have uh crazy brain says do you think
monarchy is a better type of government
of or or which other form do you think
is good for India or any other country I
think the best form of government is
benevolent
dictatorship and that's what we always
had in India who was shiram Lord Raam
was he a democratically elected prime
minister of India no he was a king which
is by definition an autocrat by
definition a king or an emperor is a
dictator who comes to power through
nepotism and passes on Power by
nepotism he is one of our civilizational
alltime greats he is an avatar of Vishnu
that's how great he
was wasn't he a
dictator what about SRI Krishna the king
of dwara at at a certain point in time
wasn't he a dictator of course he also
was the next Avatar of
Vishnu think about the golden age of
Golden Ages of India the Moran era who
were the rulers of India at the time
they were all despots and dictators
Chandra Gupta morya came to came to
power through a coup a regime change
operation a revolution he overthrew the
established government the nandha
dynasty the nandha Empire and started
the morian Empire with the help of his
mentor Shri Vishnu gup chanakya he was a
dictator asoria the most powerful of the
morian Emperors was an was a dictator
and he was a
pretty at at times pretty brutal wasn't
he Ashok but he was one of our greatest
rers of all time and I thank the gods we
had someone like Emperor asok who was
keska a dictator a military expansionist
who conquered territories all the way
from the Caspian C to the ralc and sang
in Tibet Central Asia and also the
subcontinent one of the Great rulers of
all time one of our greatest rulers of
all time who did more for our culture
than almost anybody else that we can
think of keshka what about the Gupta
Emperors what
about what what about samudra Gupta his
whole career was a military military
operation his entire career as Emperor
was one extended military
campaign he was a
dictator was were the Chola Emperors not
dict Terrors I think monarchy is the
right way to go have you seen any prime
minister of India who is even 10% of any
of these great Emperors of
ours can you think of any Prime Minister
democratically elected leader of India
who has who has even 10% of the
greatness of any of the Emperors that I
mentioned so clearly an imperial system
is what has always worked for India we
have the oldest history in the world and
it's always being in that system that
worked for us we are currently going
through a very bad
experiment of course you know there's
every system is flaws potential flaws
democracy is mediocrity ruled by the
mediocre in an imperial system if you
have a bad Emperor you're going you're
going to be in trouble if you have a bad
dictator you're going to be in trouble
yeah but have we had bad Emperors in the
past we can think of one cruel Emperor a
but even though he was
cruel India at the time was at the
height of its
Prosperity he was cruel to people around
him those who opposed him but for the
country for the subcontinent for the
civilization he was one of the greatest
of all time super
beneficial so you know more more pros
and cons way more pros and cons so I
think monarchy and an imperial system is
better for India yeah you may think I'm
old fashioned and
I'm not liberal enough or whatever
listen I'm super liberal I'm more
liberal than most liberals
actually uh okay ah the good question by
Neil yes yes yes what are your thoughts
on the new findings of the Giza Pyramid
Theory massive structures beneath them
going 2 kilometers deep yeah that's all
over social media these days that u a
team of researchers using leadar
technology have used leadar technology
to to to uh to virtually excavate the
ground beneath the the largest Pyramid
of Giza the Pyramid of King cfre I think
or whatever it's called the largest one
there are three of them outside Cairo um
and and beneath this pyramid apparently
there are these structures like you know
tunnel like structures with winding
staircases
apparently that go like hundreds of
meters down and at the base of these
tunnel like things there are these
cubical
chambers that are also massive
so according to this these
findings uh it would appear that the
Pyramid of Giza is merely the tip of the
iceberg and there's a whole structure
beneath it now first of all these this
news is come out in the form of a press
briefing or multiple press briefings
they still haven't released the research
in the form of a peer reviewed document
or or even a non-peer reviewed uh
research to report you know a scientific
paper so I would I would wait for this
actual published report to come out
whether it's reviewed or not I don't
care I want to see the published report
in written form with all the details of
what they have found the dimensions of
all the structures that they have
allegedly discovered and uh yeah that's
the first thing I would wait for at this
point in time some questions already
arise for example uh
does leadar technology have the ability
to go to to to um penetrate deep below
the soil like hundreds of meter down
meters down that's one question I have
and I'm not really sure about that I I
have to do my own research about that
how deep down can leadar penetrate
beneath the surface of the
Earth I'm sure you can go tens of meters
below the surface maybe 10 m 20 M can
you go a kilometer down can leadar
uncover structures that are a kilometer
or 2 kilm below below the surface that's
that's a big question and secondly if
even if it can can it give you very
clear details of spirals and staircases
and all that and all that you know that
sort of thing how much
detail can it uncover hundreds of meters
down if it can penetrate hundreds of
meters on so there are big questions
that arise right now I I am going to
adopt a skeptical approach until I until
the the the findings are put out in the
form of a published paper then I'll read
the paper and then I'll see if it uh
addresses the questions that I just
raised and we a to see but the proof of
the pudding is the eating so if if these
structures exist then you know
eventually there's going to be have
there's going to have to be an
archaeological U
excavation deep below the surface of the
pyramid so you let's go to the map and
let's pull out the pyramids and let me
tell you what should actually happen if
if you want to prove or disprove what is
being claimed right now so let's let's
go there where's the map here's the map
let's go to Giza so let me very rapidly
find the location of the pyramids so we
go to k
Al all right and outside of Ciro we have
Giza so we have these three pyramids
over here the Great Pyramid of Giza and
and there's two more there's kre there's
men and the Great Pyramid of Giza so
let's assume that this is the pyramid
under which you have those
structures so what you would want to
do is you you start Excavating somewhere
outside you go down let's say a couple
of hundred meters and then you so so
what you
do is you first go down a couple coup of
100 meters and then you go in the
direction of those structures and then
you try to uh hit one of the structures
through the excavation you know create a
tunnel and
then you take the tunnel and you uncover
one of the structures and try to enter
it and see if there's an actual spiral
thing that goes all the way down so that
will prove or disprove what actually is
going on that is what should happen
eventually so right now it's very early
days in this entire matter I my natural
um reaction to these things is to adopt
uh uh to be skeptical
initially and when once the once the
report is published study it properly
and then let's
see what actually comes out of it we'll
see so right now I am
skeptical but it's still exciting for
sure all right
um can I do yodling how do you learn it
I have no I I I can't do yodling
I think it's what the Swiss do in the
mountains right Ying or something I I
don't know how to learn it I'm sure you
can look it up online I I don't know
much about
yling
um okay ADI says the um I messed up my
je scored 68th person in the 12th can I
still be a good engineer I'm passionate
about manufacturing and defense I will
end up in a low tire college and I have
an interest in mechanical
engineering
um okay so you you did not get the kind
of marks that you wanted in the 12th
happens happens it's not the end of the
world you can still be a good engineer
look your performance is an in an exam
is not an indicator of the quality of
the
quality of an engineer you can be an ex
exam performance is not an indicator of
how good you can be how good an engineer
or whatever you can be so you still can
be good
engineer okay let's say you end up in
what you call a load here College
doesn't matter you know do well in the
college get high marks in that and you
know the there's a lot of opportunities
open open for you in the future so uh I
would say that don't be
discouraged sure you may not get into
the IIT or some high high tier College
like you say it doesn't matter uh do do
well in in your whatever College you get
admission in the point is like see when
it comes to exams and marks and all you
should try and get decent
marks don't try and get the highest
possible marks it's a waste of
time um in the long run at least in in
your 20s people are going to look at you
know prospective employers will look at
your marks at least when you are in your
20s so it's okay if you did not do well
in the
12th uh or in your GE but as long as you
get decent marks in college it won't
really matter so
the the the trick is to have good marks
but not great marks if you have great
marks like 99% marks it's not going to
give you a huge advantage over people
who have like like 85% marks but if you
have like 50% marks then it's going to
be a red flag over you so make sure you
don't get 50% marks get decent marks but
don't waste your time trying to be the
top kid in in class use that time to
actually acquire some skills and all
that so my point is don't be discouraged
go to college um do reasonably well in
college get good marks don't waste your
time trying to get the best possible
possible marks and learn skills and
those skills are going to be what's
valuable what's going to be valuable for
you uh in your pro in your quest to be a
mechanical engineer so do well in that
all the best and please be optimistic
and U make sure you get good marks in
the future not only to get great marks
but get good
marks
right
um Mao perz says mechanical engineer
here just dedicate yourself and study
critically passion and effort is more
important than high grades um you have
to be pract you have to have a mix of
practicality and passion so to be from
the Practical perspective you need good
good grades you don't need gr grades you
need good grades because if you get low
grades like 50% or something then it's
going to be a red flag and many
employers will will probably pass you
over for somebody else so uh get good
grades and yes I totally agree that
dedicate yourself and study critically
if you are passionate about mechanic
mechanical engineering or whatever sub
subject spend a lot of time studying it
you know Master the field acquire the
skills study critically don't memorize
actually understand the the whatever
you're
studying and uh yeah you have to put in
the effort if you're passionate about it
and you also have to be passionate about
the right things uh so yeah mechanical
engineering is is a good field to be
passionate about for sure right so get
good grades you don't need exceptionally
High grades but uh make sure you don't
get bad grades that's
all mahish shra says how did Native
Americans arrive in America what's their
ancestry uh and yeah how look there's
multiple theories about that okay how
did Native Americans arrive in America
um for the longest time there was this
uh this uh theory that uh 13,000 years
ago uh the Native Americans arrived in
America from the bearing straight so
let's go to the map and and and and and
and
and let me show you what I'm talking
about where's the
map so um we have just come out of an
Ice
Age the last Ice Age ended about roughly
10 11,000 years ago okay and then the
world started getting
warmer uh but if you the the the
Pinnacle of the last ice age was about
13,000 years ago and it started about
20,000 or so years ago so so you know
20,000 to 10,000 years before today the
world was a very different place it was
much colder the sea levels were much
much uh
lower than what they are today and for
example Sri Lanka was connected to the
Indian subcontinent it was part of the
subcontinent it was not a separate
Island uh the the all this entire region
was also connected to Asia you know the
Indonesia region Philippines region all
of that U because it was a much colder
World there was much more ice in the
world which means the ocean levels were
much lower and at that time about 13,000
years ago this region was frozen over
so the bearing straight was frozen over
and this region also was frozen over
which means there was a land connection
between uh easternmost Asia and
Alaska
right and that's why it is believed that
people from Eastern Asia the Siberian
people they were able to just walk into
Alaska and then uh over over time they
started migrating southwards as the ice
started melting over time and eventually
they ended up all the way down south
through the southernmost extremities of
South America so it was believed for the
longest time that this first uh influx
of people into the Americas happened
13,000 or so years ago and there are
some archaeological discoveries that
kind of bolstered this Theory but now we
have discovered new
archaeological sites in southern Chile
Etc that also date from 13,000 years ago
which completely destroys this theory
that humans entered the Americas only
13,000 years ago so now it's believed
maybe it happened 20,000 years ago maybe
30,000 years ago we're not quite sure
it's still a work in progress
progress now what's the ancestry of the
Native Americans the ancestry is
probably Eastern Asian or or more more
specifically Siberian people the closest
relatives of the Native Americans are
the people who are called the Siberian
peoples who live in Siberia uh the
easternmost Northern the Northeast part
of Asia very cold region sakal Katka
Siberia all of it region um see so
there's significant uh genetic um
similarities between the Native
Americans and the Siberian people
yeah
okay
um what other questions do we
have he mon says if time is linear and
everything in the universe is
predetermined can Free Will Truly exist
uh
how do we know everything in the
universe is predetermined do we have
evidence of that there is one physics
theory called super determinism that
says that yeah perhaps everything is
pred predetermined and what is the
origin of the theory we know that the
best theory of we have of the origin of
the universe that we inhabit is what is
colloquially called The Big Bang Theory
right that everything that the Universe
expanded out of a single super dense
point about 13.8 billion years ago a
super luminal expansion initially and
that's what gave rise to the universe so
it was not an explosion it was an
expansion of space and time and
everything within it that's called The
Big Bang Theory so if that theory is
true which it most likely is that's the
best theory we have the part of the
Lambda Lambda CDM model of cosmology
then uh what we have is that
U so every single particle that exists
in in the
universe its origin can be traced back
to the big bag to this to this to the
moment when the universe started
expanding out of a single point more or
less a single point and so everything
can be uh so the so the evolution of
every particle of matter and every piece
of energy let's say can be U determined
using differential equations and of
course there there's going to be some
Randomness in it because of the inherent
random nature statistical uh stochastic
nature of quantum mechanics but that
Randomness is genuinely random it's not
predetermined so in that case you're
going to have some Randomness because of
U uh because of the nature of quantum
mechanics but apart from that everything
else is pred predetermined because of
differential equations which so if that
is
true then Free Will cannot
exist okay so in that case Free Will is
an
illusion uh but yeah so it's
a so from that Theory's perspective it
may mean that Free Will is an illusion
but it goes against everything we
believe in uh and if you start believing
that Free Will is an illusion and
everything is just pred determined then
you kind of kind of some people may give
up on life so I my point is that we
don't quite know which theory is true
which is
not uh we don't we should not pretend to
believe that our understanding of
science is is that that we understand
the universe very well we understand the
universe very very poorly we understand
less than 5% of the universe if at all
you know so um we have a very
rudimentary understanding of the
universe so we what we our understanding
may have a lot of flaws in it so I would
not say that it is uh a fact that the
universe is predetermined and everything
that happens is predetermined so let's
that's not an assumption we should make
is time linear we not quite sure about
that also so you know if you if you
start mixing philosophy and religion
into science then you will say the time
is cyclical and all that stuff
well you know if you look at the way
time is evolved on this as far as we we
we we are concerned from the beginning
of the universe 13.8 billion years ago
time seems to have been fairly fairly
linear of course we know that time
evolves differently different parts of
the universe depending on how much
matter exists because the presence of
mass slows time down and the absence of
mass time flows time the the rate at
which clocks evolve is different it's
faster so if you are sitting on the
surface of the planet here like the way
I am a clock that I'll watch or clock
I'll wear will will tick at a certain
rate but if I am 300 kilm above the
surface of the Earth that same watch
will will take faster slightly very
slightly faster and if I am outside the
solar system it will take even
faster so time itself Flows at different
rates and different parts of the
universe and that itself may be the the
reason
why you know certain phenomena exist so
you know it's it's pretty complicated
time is well from our perspective linear
but it flows it it it flows at different
rates at different parts of the
universe and uh there is no guarantee
that everything in the universe is
predetermined so I would say that it's
it's okay to believe in Free Will and
it's okay to put in a lot of effort in
life instead of just being a passive
Idol spectator rather than an active
participant please be active
participants in life and please try to
make a dent in the universe and try to
shape the shape of the future instead of
just being a supporting actor in the in
the grand scheme of be the main
character don't be a supporting actor
right
okay sparkling Lotus says so our
calculations of the speed of light have
got to be inaccurate
no
no no it doesn't mean that where does it
mean that
see we there are different ways of
calculating the speed of light U I'll
not go into that but it doesn't mean
it's
inaccurate um It's actually an
interesting question that you're
asking uh because see time Flows at
different speeds right the clock will be
slower on Earth as as opposed to in
space where there is no mass in all so
if you measure the speed of light in in
space it may seem to be slightly
different in all but we have an overall
understanding of what is the speed of
light Across the Universe and the speed
of light according to general relativity
is the same
so what happens to the speed of light
I'll
explain the presence of a massive object
like the Sun or a black hole doesn't
slow light
down it doesn't slow slow the speed of
light it simply changes the trajectory
of light it bends SpaceTime so light
travels in curved paths because of the
presence of gravity but it doesn't slow
light down the speed of light Remains
the Same whether it is in free space or
whether it is near a massive
object so our calculations of the speed
of light will never be
inaccurate okay so yeah interesting
question and that's the answer okay we
are almost at the end of
today's session let's take maybe a
couple more questions Amisha says do uh
do you believe in multi- Universe I
think it's possible that we may have a
Multiverse look we have no way of
looking beyond our universe we can't
even see the entirety of our universe we
probably can see only a small portion of
our overall Universe the the the the uh
Cosmic Horizon is about
995 uh billion light years that's how
far we can see and every day it's it's
getting you know more and
more objects are moving beyond it
because of the
expansion of the universe so we only are
able to observe a small portion of our
actual Universe the actual universe that
we inhabit may be much larger but I
think it's
it's quite possible that we may have
that we may have a Multiverse kind of
scenario now that is pure speculation
that is not a scientific statement it is
probably a philosophical or spiritual
statement I'm making but I think it's
possible that if you have a universe
that we inhabit there may be other
universes
also um and there are reasons why one
can speculate that way um there are two
scientific theories that give rise to
the philosophical concept of the
Multiverse uh one is is the string
theory landscape which uh gives you the
possibility of 10 raised to 500 possible
different universes okay that's a string
theory landscape and secondly we have
the Manny world's interpretation of
quantum mechanics which also is taken
quite seriously by many scientists many
many physicists and that also gives you
a Multiverse scenario so there are
scenarios in which Multiverse uh
Multiverse kind of in which multiple
universes can exist but there's no way
of proving or disproving that so even
though it's a valid interpretation of
quantum mechanics it's a philosophical
rather than a practical interpretation
or a scientific interpretation of
quantum mechanics all
right uh let's take one final question
Shadow says do you listen to any Indian
rapper do you listen to any Indian
rapper I think once you can ask I don't
listen to any Indian rappers I am not a
fan of rap music I don't think it's
music at all and I please don't be
offended if you
if you are a fan of rap music you don't
have to agree with everything I say but
I don't really uh enjoy it last question
Karan says your ancestors were Guardians
of the somat shivling uh yes not guards
Guardians there's something called the
chavda dynasty the chavda dynasty ruled
Gujarat parts of Gujarat between the
between let's say the seventh and the
between the eth and 10th Century
ad that was my family my family is
pretty large okay so they were the
rulers of Gujarat and as such it was
their job to
protect the snat
jerling so they were the servants and
Guardians of the snat shivling by being
the rulers of Gujarat so snat came under
their protection zat came under the
protection of the cha chavda Kings of
the time uh yeah so they were the
Guardians of the snat shling so I have a
personal connection with the snat shling
indeed all right with that we will go we
will bring this session to an end it's
been way more than two hours very
interesting very enjoyable uh let me
know in the comments whether you find
this sort of session more interesting in
which I take questions from the live
chat or do you prefer qu do you prefer
sessions in which I take pre-chosen
questions questions I have looked
through the questions that I've selected
from the comments do you prefer that
sort of session or do you prefer session
which is more interactive and I take
just these questions from the live chat
itself please let me know in the
comments below and thank you so much
everybody for all your questions I
really enjoyed today's session and I
will see you in next week's live stream
once again very soon until then take
care keep asking
questions keep raising your standards
take care see you soon bye-bye